A Guide to the Colonial Leesburg, Inc. Collection, ca. 1949-1954
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Colonial Leesburg, Inc. Collection ca. 1949-1954
Thomas Balch Library
SC 0029
16 folders
Colonial Leesburg, Inc. Collection documents the establishment and accomplishments of Colonial Leesburg, Inc., a nonprofit organization founded to preserve Leesburg's colonial-style buildings.
Unknown, B. Powell Harrison
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
B. Powell Harrison, Leesburg, VA; unknown
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
2002.0013, 1995.0073X
Historical Information
Colonial Leesburg, Inc. was founded in 1949 by B. Powell Harrison, Jr. (25 Aug 1911-1 Nov 2000) to preserve "early American" architecture in businesses in downtown Leesburg. Colonial Leesburg held numerous open houses and gatherings to encourage appreciation of Leesburg's historical landmarks. Much of modern Leesburg, including its brick sidewalks and colonial-style buildings, is a product of this nonprofit corporation's efforts.
Scope and Content
The Colonial Leesburg, Inc. Collection documents the establishment and accomplishments of Colonial Leesburg, Inc., a nonprofit organization founded to preserve Leesburg's colonial-style buildings. Elements of the collection (pamphlets, blueprints, press releases, and newspaper clippings) are in overall good condition but should be handled carefully.
The first item in the collection is a pamphlet entitled "Opportunity Leesburg and You." It emphasizes Leesburg's major sites, including Washington's Headquarters and the Janney House, and states that Colonial Leesburg seeks to "encourage and facilitate" building restoration, and to generate information about Leesburg's history and heritage throughout the community. The collection contains an annual report from November 1950, describing the first fiscal year as "successful" and listing architectural plans, consultations, and projects. Architectural notes and sketches for downtown Leesburg's renovation are also included. "Suggested Outline: Leesburg Open House" proposes plans for an organizational event that hopes to draw at least a thousand guests. Reports from various meetings, newspaper clippings discussing the organization's goals, and a press release documenting the success of the Open House are among the succeeding items. A transcript of the "Leesburg" pamphlet, written and distributed by the organization, notes Leesburg landmarks such as the Rust House, the Welbourn House and Garden, the Clerk's Office, and the Tally-Ho Theater. There are also reports from the organization's Sidewalk Committee, which worked with the town to promote the use of brick for sidewalks in the historic parts of Leesburg.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Colonial Leesburg, Inc (SC 0029), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA
Other Finding Aid
None
Technical Requirements
None
Related Material
None
Contents List
- "Opportunity Leesburg and You" Pamphlets n.d.
- Annual Report: November 1950 November 1950
- Architectural Plans for Downtown Leesburg n.d.
- "Suggested Outline: Leesburg Open House" n.d.
- Meeting minutes 1950-19511950-1951
- Sidewalk Committee reports 1949, n.d. 1949, n.d.
- Press Release May 2, 1950 2 May 1950
- Correspondence 1950, 1954 1950, 1954
- Committee Resolutions on Colonial Leesburg Week n.d.
- "Leesburg" Pamphlets n.d.
- Transcript of "Leesburg" Pamphlet n.d.
- Picture of Colonial Downtown Leesburg n.d.
- Newspaper Article: "A Date with Beauty" n.d.
- Newspaper Article: "Leesburg Opens Fight to Restrain Modernism" n.d.
- Picture of West Loudoun Street, late 1940s late 1940s
- Newspaper Article: "Colonial Leesburg Gets Charter, Names Officers" n.d.